A Guide to the Josiah Gilbert Holland Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #7729
Josiah Gilbert Holland Collection 1860-1881
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
7729
ca. 20 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit, 1964 Nov 11
Item Listing
- Letters
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to C. C. Shackford, 1860 Oct 19; ALS, 1 p.
    [Will give lecture if his schedule permits.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to "My Dear Sir", 1865 Oct 22; ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines invitation to lecture because of prior commitment.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Edward DeForest, 1867 Sep 18; ALS, 1 p.
    [Gives lecture schedule.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Mr. Rich, 1867 Oct 1; ALS, 1 p.
    [Proposes the title "The Woman Question" for an upcoming lecture.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Thomas Dana, 1870 Jun 7; ALS, 1 p.
    [Has no plans to lecture this season; may change his mind.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Henry Howard, 1873 Mar 5; ALS, 1 p.
    [Congratulates him on election as governor of Rhode Island; appreciates Howard's remarks on his novel,
    Arthur Bonnicastle
    . ]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1875 Aug 12; ALS, 1 p.
    [Regrets he has no photograph to send; promises to send one later.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Col. George E. Waring, Jr., 1876 Feb 2; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says lost gloves not his; may belong to Col. [Thomas Wentworth] Higginson or Mr. Ayer; does not believe [Bret] Harte's book sold for $10,000.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1876 May 26; ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines to send an old poem for publication; does not have the strength to write a new one.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1876 Oct 16; ALS, 1 p.
    [Will send letter from [Richard Watson] Gilder regarding stories submitted by Boyesen.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to "Dear Sir", 1877 Mar 27; ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines invitation to lecture.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1877 Apr 20; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says Clemens Petersen wishes to write a paper on Bjornsen; asks if this will interfere with his plans.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1878 Jan 30; ALS, 1 p.
    [Suggests an illustrated article on the educational life of European universities.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Will C. Pershing, 1878 Feb 11; ALS, 1 p. w/env
    [Declines an invitation to write for Pershing's magazine because of his own duties to his own magazine.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Hjalmar Hjorth Boyesen, 1878 Feb 25; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says
    Scribner's Monthly
    is interested in [Boyesen's] "A Daughter of the Philistines."]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to "Dear Sir", 1879 Jan 24; ALS, 1 p.
    [Remarks that he and [Richard Watson] Gilder cannot understand the last lines of material submitted; asks him to look it over again.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to "Dear Sir", 1880 Feb 21; ALS, 2 p.
    [Has seen Mrs. Conyer; praises her hard work and successful experiment.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Williams, 1880 May 4; ALS, 1 p.
    [Congratulates him on his article entitled "The Government of Large Cities"; praises its moral insight and moral earnestness.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to [Richard Watson] Gilder, 1880 Jun 12; ALS, 2 p.
    [Gives his opinion of Walt Whitman; belittles him and his talent as a poet; comments that Mrs. Thaxter's fever is strong.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to [Richard Watson] Gilder, 1880 Sep 19; ALS, 3 p.
    [Likes Stedman's work on Walt Whitman because of its critical view of the subject; calls Whitman's art a "monster" and a "bastard"; does not believe he made a contribution to American literature; compares him unfavorably to other American literary figures such as Poe, Longfellow, Lowell, Whittier, and Stedman.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Admiral [George Henry] Preble, 1881 Oct 10; ALS, 1 p.
    [Politely refuses to publish his book.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to William B[uell] Sprague, n.y. Sep 4; ALS, 2 p.
    [Will print his pamphlet; insists it be done in Springfield; dislikes having a local print job done at a firm a hundred miles away.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Mrs. Foote, ALS, 1 p.
    [Declines invitation to visit because his wife is sick.]
  - Josiah Gilbert Holland to Mr. Marvin, ANS, 1 p.
    [Reports that his own story, "Mistress of the Manse," is now ready to be printed.]